Part of what makes food like this good
is human error. In the same way that a
baguette is good because of human error.
If you made a perfect baguette, it
tastes like Costco.
So, today we're going to be talking
about the Mongolians and their
contributions to what might have been
the most profitable corner of the
biggest land empire ever known to
humankind.
Which is a slightly sensitive topic
depending on where you are in the world
right now, but we'll try our best to
keep it to the food. The food today,
that's right, more historical [__]
with food. The food we're going to talk
about today is yang rou chuan. Or
skewered mutton. Skewered mutton kebabs
roasted over open coal and spiced
halfway through with cumin, which is an
impossible feat of flavors if it were
not for the introduction of the DLC of
Eurasia to central China via my boy
Kublai Khan or the Great Khan, the
leader of the dynasty, the Yuan dynasty.
So, let me give you a little bit of
background, all right? In northern
China, especially in the northwest, the
idea that we eat beef and mutton more so
than people in the south and we use
spices like cumin was not a Chinese
thing. So, before the Mongols, Han food
is pork and vegetable heavy. It's Song
dynasty food, delicate, intricate,
balanced, poetic. And then in came the
Mongols [music] on their big sexy horses
and said, "Beef, bitch."
"Mutton, bitch."
"Spices, bitch." And that's why we got
things like rou wan zi and yang rou
chuan and cumin zi ran and spices and
roasting over open coals.
We'll talk more about that later. Today
we're going to teach you the
northeastern, the Dongbei version of
yang rou chuan, which is arguably the
most popular version in mainland China.
Our recipe or my colleague Charlie's
recipe or yang ge
He's going to be teaching you his dry
rub and we're going to be bullshitting
and talking a little bit about history.
So, before we start, to test my southern
colleagues, who was the Great Khan of
the dynasty?
Genghis Khan.
There you go.
His baba
This is our second take. You're just
memorizing what they had the first time.
So, in the early 13th century, Temüjin,
as you would know him, is Genghis Khan,
which is the wrong pronunciation. The
proper one is Chinggis Khan, or Chinggis
Khan, the soft "h", short soft "h" with
a long "a". Chinggis Khan, in Mandarin,
Cheng Ji Si Han, was the first person to
unify Mongolia. He had four boys:
Ögedei, Chagatai, Jochi, and Tolui.
Ögedei was not supposed to be the ruler
of the entire Mongol Empire. It was his
brothers, the fighty, jacked, angry,
violent Chagatai and Jochi. But, Ögedei
was very good at drinking and making
friends. We got to do anything to do
with them.
So, when the Great Khan, Genghis, made
his announcement, says, "I have decided
on which son will inherit my empire."
Both Chagatai and Jochi said, "Him."
All we know how to do is [__] people up.
Ögedei can actually rule an empire. And
then Genghis Khan went, "You want to
join them?"
Yeah, okay, [__] it, sure. Ögedei,
congratulations. You have inherited the
entire empire. And then Jochi and
Chagatai, they took over the Golden
Horde and the what are they doing now?
Tolui, the youngest son,
Kublai.
He was our emperor. How does that
pertain to food? You have to understand
that a lot of what Chinese people even
consider Chinese food, especially in the
north, especially in Beijing, Beijing,
are actually not even Chinese
historically. Because before the
Mongols, before Kublai, nobody lived in
Dadu, Dadu, or as you would know it,
Peking, or if you're modern, Beijing,
was not the capital before the Mongols.
Dadu, or the Great Capital, was a Mongol
feat. They moved the capital there. And
then all of a sudden, the court was full
of Turks, Mongols, Arabs, as in Muslims,
and Persians.
That is actually Persian kofta.
With some spices translated into Mongol,
then translated into Han for Chinese
cooks. You can see a lot of these
recipes from the Yuan Dynasty look not
Chinese because of this mix of things.
So, Chinese food was forever changed by
the Mongols because literally they
plugged us into Eurasia. They made us
international food wise. They secured
and made the Silk Road safe, which is
where [__] like this and all of this
comes from. Besides the chili, not the
chili, but all of the other stuff,
right? Came via the Silk Road because
when you have a safe trading route, you
have spices. And spices came in on the
backs of traders and merchants. One of
our biggest treatises on diets and
dietetics is book called The Keys to
Food and Drink,
which is a book written by
He was most likely a Se
First of all, the boys behind the
cameras are Cantonese people. They
really don't know what I'm [__]
talking about here because back during
Mongol rule, it went Mongols, then Semu
Ren, then Beihan Ren, then Nanhan Ren.
So, you guys were on the [__] bottom
rung of the ladder during the Yuan
Dynasty, which is why the food, the
steaming, the stews is all so far
removed from northern Chinese food. The
Semu Ren are all the not Hans that are
maybe Muslim.
Were the Semu Ren, the colored Central
Asians.
So, most likely
was a Semu Ren. His name, the middle
Chinese pronunciation would have been
which was most likely the Chinese
version of Hussein,
which is a Middle Eastern Eurasian name.
It was a mixture of cooking, but also
Islamic Muslim medicine. So, you know
how Chinese have traditional Chinese
medicine and
Not like warm sexy.
>> Sing as in its nature is is warm. It's
warm and uh wudu it's non-toxic. So a
lot of modern Chinese ideas of like this
is a warm meat. This one's dry and hot.
This one's wet and cold. It's actually
there's a lot of Muslim traditional
medicine in it as well. A little bit
more about food.
>> So the ingredients you'll need are
actually quite simple. Our chili powder,
cumin, garlic and ginger, onions, and
some lamb. Our supplier is Cantonese. So
when I asked him for lamb meat, he got
me lamb bones. Because when they think
lamb,
>> make soup. Which is why he gave me an
inappropriate meat for making skewers.
So we had to order extra. So this is a
perfect example of what not the [__] to
do. Get meat. Meaty meaty meat. [music]
>> In the same way that the hierarchy of
people was Mongol, Semu, and Northern
Han and Southern Han, the food was at
the very top for the first time in
Chinese history, lamb and mutton was
right up top. Then it was beef. Then it
was pork. And then it was like fish and
grains. And in the north we eat wheat
and millet for the first time. In the
south it was still rice and rice and
rice. Generally speaking. For the
barbecue, you need two things besides
the meat. The marinade and the powder on
top. There's been someone in the comment
section asking for the the powder, the
seasoning mix for a long time now. And
the guy who makes the best seasoning mix
is actually my colleague here, Charlie.
And I only just found out today that he
doesn't have a recipe. He just buys
ready-made [__] and then mixes
ready-made [__] He's not starting from
spices. But the recipe is quite simple.
It's usually some nuts, sesame and
peanuts, some spices. Usually cumin and
chili. But there's also things like
shiyong putao tang. This is a very messy
one. This is a little bit more pure.
This is just chili, MSG, sesame,
hydrogenated palm kernel oil. Okay, it's
not that clean. So these are all
industrial grade mixes. So Charlie will
show you his recipe while I show you
mine. Once again, I've never done this
with a recipe,
so I'm going to make the recipe as we go
here, okay? 30 g of chili powder, 10 g
of cumin powder, mixed with Yeah, 10 g
of sesame, not too much or you'll burn
it. Mixed with 10 g of MSG. Do you hear
that sound? This is the sound of white
people fainting.
20 g of salt, 5 g of white pepper, 5 g
of Sichuan peppercorns. If you don't
have them, you can use sancho, and
that's pretty much it for me. If you
want, you can add peanuts into this, but
I don't want to kill any white people.
So,
let's not put peanuts in here.
Food processor, spice grinder, use a
pestle and mortar, whatever you feel
like. You can buy everything that I just
used pre-ground. Or just buy some sha
cha fen. If you don't feel like making
one, just don't make one. And this is my
powder. Amazing. Now, everybody watch
watching closely as Charlie demonstrated
his chuan jia pei fang, generations of
refinement and experimentation. Wow,
look at this highly technical maneuver.
It looks like he's a traditional Chinese
like Chinese medicine doctor creating
like a very secret blend of heal-all
[__] but what he's literally doing
is mixing like Hellmann's mayonnaise
with Heinz ketchup with French's mustard
and adding a little bit of Lea &
Perrins. That's all he's doing. All
right, so over here I have a bunch of
lamb meat. Before we get started, I must
tell you guys that from this point
moving forward, when I use the word
tender, I mean Asian tender. I don't
mean white tender. And I don't mean to
sound obtuse or prejudiced when I say
this, East Asians and Westerners view
tender very differently. For you, it's
don't have to chew it at all. For
example, tenderloin and purees and
strained sauces. In the West, ostensibly
in Eurocentric food, the lack of texture
is the texture of penis. For us, even
our emperors ate like chicken kneecaps
and chickens feet and the gristle.
Chewing was not relegated to the
activity of the poor. Here I've selected
some lamb leg, could be lamb shoulder,
lamb chop, could be lamb sirloin, lamb
whatever the [__] you feel like. And you
want to chop it down into about half a
thumb size chunks or as you would call
it in America an inch. If you have
partly frozen meat, this is also a great
and forgiving application. You don't
even have to bother
thawing it out all the way. Just chop it
down into chunks and marinate it as
such. Please also do not feel the need
to be precious about the actual
uniformity of size. Part of the joys
of having drunk late night skewers with
your homies is that in every skewer
every piece of meat is a slightly
different texture.
Yeah. So in our hometown there's a a
district, the Muslim district. We call
it very rudely the Muslim camp.
There's an actual name for it. It is the
the front of Huilong and Mukden Shenyang
is home to the oldest mosque in China.
It was built in 1627. When we used to
get packed up in the Korean
neighborhood, you would just kind of
stumble over there drunk a few
kilometers away. I don't know how we
made it. By the time we got there it
would have been like
5:00 6:00 in the morning and then you
could hear like the Fajr, the first call
to prayer.
And then they would do the praying and
the sacrificing of the lamb and they go
and murder the lamb and the beef and
slice it up. Twang and you see like the
boys come out with their hats and like
make the skewers and you'd still be kind
of drunk watching them do it and it was
[__] sick. And then you would just
watch them cook it up. I would want to
like come drink with me bro, the night's
not over and they're like dude we can't
drink with you. I'M LIKE WHY NOT? AND
I'D PASS out in the Muslim quarter, wake
up and then I'll be like oh [__] did I
try to make you guys drink with me
again? They're like, "Yeah, you did."
I'm like, "I'm so sorry." They're like,
"No, it's fine. Get the [__] out of
here." Anyways, inside this bowl goes my
chunks. From here, there's two things
you can do. I have here some sliced
onions. You can throw them in like this.
If you wanted to have a more oniony
flavor, you can juice the onion or blitz
the onion in a food processor. For me, I
would just squeeze it first to bruise it
and get some of the juices out cuz I
don't want the onion to burn later when
it goes in the coals. So,
onions go in.
Smush smush smush. You won't be eating
these. They don't go in the skewer.
They're just here for the marinade. All
right? Now, uh here with uh Vincent's
brand new microplane goes in a little
bit of ginger. How much is up to you? I
don't want to taste the ginger. I just
want it to get rid of some of the
laminess and also help tenderize the
meat. The enzymatic action inside ginger
will actually tenderize proteins. And
also some garlic. If you want to chop it
up, you can. Uh not too much cuz garlic
will burn under the direct heat of the
coals.
So, me and him have a lot of
differences. I will always go in with a
little bit of soy sauce cuz it is a
Chinese version of Eurasian food after
all. But that being said, I will once
again go in with my favorite white soy
and then in goes my salt and you just go
for it. Massage the crap out of it.
Cool. Perfect. So, this might be another
difference with most skewered foods. We
never almost never season the meat
itself. You go on to the grill and then
you halfway through you go
and then shake it with the top
seasoning. Now, this is a very very lean
mix. I recommend that you also add
chunks of pure lamb fat in there because
that's what makes it tasty. That being
said, I also have to [__] some more
and wait for the lamb that I just
ordered to come in so I can get more fat
in here. But after you're done with So
step, you just let it marinate for a
couple hours at the very least,
preferably overnight. Yeah?
Yeah, so this is what you want it to
smell like before the roast.
You want it to be oniony, garlicky,
gingery, very Chinese at this point,
right? Besides the Western leek, the
yang cong, right? But you want it to
smell very Asian Asiany. So, let's
review. Any lamb you like, chop it into
small chunks. Inside the marinade goes
salt. Aim for 1% by weight of salt if
you must have a ratio. A little bit soy
sauce if you so wish. Onion, garlic,
ginger. Your spice mix is chili powder,
cumin powder, salt, MSG, sesame, peanut
if you can handle it, and a little bit
of Sichuan peppercorn and white pepper.
That's my mix. His mix is whatever
ready-made powder you have. Use Montreal
steak spice if you feel like it. But if
you want to make your own, that's what
you make. Yeah? Any questions so far? Is
there any more you want to
>> What's the difference between this one
and the Xinjiang shao mai?
>> This is difficult one. So, chuan, the
idea of chuan on skewers, it didn't
really exist in the Yuan Dynasty. The
Yuan Dynasty was zhi rou. It's a Middle
Chinese Ancient Chinese word. It looks
like a little tomahawk steak on top of a
fire. It literally means to roast meat
over fire. To answer your question, back
then it was just the roasting of lamb.
And then you would put the fermenting
dairy inside
or the stock inside to soften the lamb
and then roast it zhi over coals or hot
fire. It was only later with the
introduction of Uyghur food and Turkic
influence and spice influence and
modernization and standardization that
it turned into the skewers that we know
today. And because of the huge Muslim
influence on Dunhuang food culture,
that's why we are known as the place
where good skewers are.
It's more heavily spiced and some would
argue more representative of what
medieval Chinese Muslims would higher up
would have made. Historically speaking,
the the Chinese Muslims of Muqtan, our
hometown, would have been, generally
speaking, wealthier and higher up in
station than Muslims from the elsewheres
of the country.
They were allowed to live in near the
Imperials, near the Manchu. Right? To
our western audience, we didn't really
learn the amount we should have learned
as deep as we should have learned it
here
about this particular part of history.
It's not a problem specific to us.
America doesn't learn about anything
outside of America, Europe doesn't learn
about America, we don't learn about
Europe. It's the same [__] The Japanese
also have a very interesting version
of what happened in the past 100 years.
Right? So, it's not just us. Now, the
biggest shame is this part of our
history, and I do consider it to be our
history,
is unfortunately and unfairly viewed by
a lot of people historically and even to
this day
as not Chinese. Foreign rulers, the
Mongols. But, the Mongols,
for better or for worse,
did give us access to some of the best
technologies, maths, medicines, culture,
Eurasia, the Middle East, the entire
Mongol Empire. And it heavily shaped
what we eat and do today. Did I answer
your question?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, so essentially this process is the
exact reason why people in my hometown
who want to open a like because the
businesses you want to open
Yeah, cuz what the [__] else are you
going to invest in?
They are not even tell as good. If you
gave a straight northern man the choice
between, you know, or hanging out in a
room full of and taking a bath, we pick
the second one. Yeah. Northern bathhouse
culture is crazy. Imagine like a Roman
palace, but it's just one bathhouse, and
it costs like 20, 30 USD to live in
absolute luxury, hang out in the water.
>> I really want to try that.
>> Do you enjoy being naked around people?
>> No.
>> You have [music] to be naked.
>> Okay.
>> If you're not fully naked immediately,
there's something wrong with you.
>> You guys won't be embarrassed?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> You're gay if you [__] wear a towel
in the bathhouse. There are only three
places a towel is allowed to go in
Dongbei. You're allowed to have it over
your shoulder, under your armpit, and
when you're sitting down over your head
like this. If you try to cover your
[__] you gay.
>> Really?
>> Yes.
So, here's what you do, right? You go to
Dongbei, you go to a bathhouse, and then
you put on your headphones, and then you
just listen to Nat Geo music. Like, you
know National Geographic?
>> Yeah.
>> Where David Attenborough is like, "Here
we see the Benjamin and the right?" Just
imagine you're watching a Nat Geo
episode. We behave like animals. First
thing you do is you walk into the place
with your towel over your shoulder ditch
out AND YOU GO
>> [groaning]
>> AND YOU SIT DOWN, AND THERE'S ALWAYS AN
OLD guy with his floating in the water.
He goes, "Yeah, sit next to me." And you
sit down, cross your legs, and then you
just talk about like, "Hey, how's your
[__] wife? Sick." And then somehow a
6-year-old
will come rolling by and his little pink
is right in your face, and he's jumping
and playing in the water, and you're
trying to have a serious time. Yeah,
man, bathhouses are serious. I was that
6-year-old boy at some point. Anyways,
so here's what you want a skewer to look
like. This one's quite lean, but also
serviceable. And it goes across your
coals like that. Unlike in most
Eurocentric cooking, where you slap it
on and you don't touch it, you want to
be turning these every minute or two,
similar to a kubideh in Persian food.
Now, over here Charlie has prepared a
little deli of oil to brush on top just
in case the coloring isn't going as fast
as we want it to, but it will also help
later for the seasoning powder to stick.
Do not put your spices on right now.
Now, if you want it to have more color
on the outside and less doneness on the
inside, you want really high heat. So,
start aerating your coals very, very
hard. If you ever come to visit China or
you ever come home and you go to a
skewer place, and the skewers are very
evenly brown? That usually means they
weren't made on coals. They were thrown
in a deep fryer.
Taste lazy. Because part of what makes
food like this good is human error. In
the same way that a baguette is good
because of human error. If you made a
perfect baguette, it tastes like Costco.
All right. So, at this point, it's very
heavily colored, and maybe like 80% of
the way done. Or as you would call it a
medium well in the west. This is when I
throw on my powders. And don't be afraid
to let some of it go onto the coals and
burn and create smoke. It's all part of
the flavor. Remember, you are not only
seasoning, you are smoking these as
well. Woo!
>> Wow.
>> That's exactly the doneness you want.
This is how you would serve. So, where
we're from, you don't order how many or
half a dozen or full dozen.
Look at that. Isn't that beautiful?
Makes me so happy.
And you can also finish a little bit on
top at the end.
And that gives it some fresh spice
flavors.
All right, guys. Dig in.
So, the dish guy doesn't have to wash it
later.
All right. [__] yeah.
Oh, [__] yeah. I got a piece of gristle
on the first bite, and that's my
favorite part. So, this is the doneness
you want. Just cooked through, heavily
charred on the corners.
And if you squeeze hard enough, some
pink juice, but mostly done. Here you
go.
Yeah.
Marvel skewer. All right. I'm going to
finish skewering these up. Thank you so
much for your time. If you like this
episode, comment, like, subscribe. Let
me know down in the comments section
below. Comment, like, subscribe. And
comment, like, subscribe. We will do
more of this kind of content. It's
entirely up to you what I make because I
want to know what you guys watch. Most
of my time is spent making Chinese
content. So, I'd much rather prefer not
to have to think about what I have to
make here. Just make whatever you guys
want to see. So, comment like subscribe.
And we'll talk off and talk soon. Take
care. Bye-bye. What do you guys want to
make next?
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> This is the heart of northern cooking.
It's a [__] here.